Guide to the Records of the Center for Ballet and the Arts RG.37.51
New York University Archives
Records for the Center for Ballet and the Arts
2014-2017
New York University Archives
New York University. The Center for Ballet and the Arts
RG.37.51
710 Gigabytes in 184 video files and 5 image files.
The Center for Ballet and the Arts at New York University is an international institute for scholars and artists of ballet and its related arts and sciences. Since its establishment in 2014, the Center's mission is to bring to the art of ballet new ideas and the full resources of a major research university, and to bring ballet into the university as a serious subject of study and research within the context of the history of culture. This collection consists of 183 video files and five image files of Center events and performances between 2014 and 2017. Events documented in this collection include seminars, lectures, demonstrations, presentations, and performances by students, faculty, and guests, including filmmaker Frederick Wiseman; Heather Watts, former principal ballerina for the New York City Ballet; choreographer and former ballet dancer Alexei Ratmansky; and former dancer and entrepreneur John Michael Schert. Most of the events took place in New York University classroom or performance spaces. Events focused on a variety of topics relating to dance history, practice, and innovative performance.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 183 digital video files and five digital image files of events and performances produced by New York University's Center for Ballet and the Arts between 2014 and 2017.
Events documented in this collection include seminars, lectures, demonstrations, presentations, and performances by students, faculty, and guests, including filmmaker Frederick Wiseman; Heather Watts, former principal ballerina for the New York City Ballet; choreographer and former ballet dancer Alexei Ratmansky; and former dancer and entrepreneur John Michael Schert. Most of the events took place in New York University classroom or performance spaces. Events focused on a variety of topics relating to dance history, practice, and innovative performance.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in rough chronological order in the manner they were received from the donor.
Historical Note
The Center for Ballet and the Arts at New York University is an international institute for scholars and artists of ballet and its related arts and sciences. Since its establishment in 2014, the Center's mission is to bring to the art of ballet new ideas and the full resources of a major research university, and to bring ballet into the university as a serious subject of study and research within the context of the history of culture.
Conditions Governing Access
Three videos are restricted and require permission of the donor for access. All other materials are open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by Emily Rasmussen on behalf of the Center for Ballet and the Arts in February 2017 with a further accretion in February 2018. The accession associated with these transfers are 2017.009 and 2018.005, respectively.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of on site video records. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only.
Accruals
Further accruals are expected.
Dance.; Dance -- Study and teaching; Ballet -- New York (State) -- New York; Video recordings.; Performing arts -- United States.
- Center for Ballet and the Arts Videos
  - LIVE from the NYPL conversation with Alexei Ratmansky, 2014-10-08; cuid2081; 4.1 Gigabytes in 3 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_1)
    Scope and Contents
    Event Type: Conversations on Ballet
    Speaker: Paul Holdengraber, curator; Alexei Ratmansky, choreographer
    Speaker Type: Invited Guest
    Location: NYPL
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original materials are available for research onsite in the University Archives reading room. Prior notice is required for access.
    Ratmanskiĭ, Alekseĭ, 1968-
  - Seminar: David Velleman, 2014-10-16; cuid2092; 2.99 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_60)
    Event Type: Seminar on Ballet
    Speaker: David Velleman
    Speaker Type: Resident Fellow, CBA
    Location: 20 Cooper Square
    Audio/visual materials are available for research onsite in the University Archives reading room. Prior notice is required for access.
  - Seminar: Heather Watts, 2014-12-03; cuid2093; 30.6 Gigabytes in 4 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_2)
    Speaker: Heather Watts
  - Seminar: Frederick Wiseman, 2014-11-20; cuid2094; 26.2 Gigabytes in 3 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_3)
    Speaker: Frederick Wiseman
  - Seminar: Christopher d'Amboise, 2014-12-04; cuid2095; 48.3 Gigabytes in 3 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_4)
    Speaker: Christopher d'Amboise
  - Convening: John Michael Schert, 2014-12-10; cuid2096; 24.8 Gigabytes in 4 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_5)
    Speaker: John Michael Schert
  - Music and Dance: A Composer's Workshop, 2015-04-13; cuid2098; 3.7 Gigabytes in 2 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_6)
    Speaker: Scott Wheeler
  - Proposal for a Dance, 2015-04-22; cuid2099; 4.38 Gigabytes in 3 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_7)
    Speaker: Suzanne Vega
  - Talks on Ballet -- Grace in the Twentieth Century, 2015-03-31; cuid2100; 2.97 Gigabytes in 2 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_8)
    Speaker: Dr. Susan Jones
  - LIVE from the NYPL Conversation with Suzanne Farrell, 2015-05-12; cuid2101; 936 Megabytes in 3 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_9)
    Event Type: Talks on Ballet
    Speaker: Paul Holdengraber, curator; Suzanne Farrell, choreographer/dancer
  - Seminar: Adriana Pierce, 2015-05-21; cuid2103; 1.91 Gigabytes in 2 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_10)
    Speaker: Adriana Pierce
  - Seminar: Ariel Rose, 2015-05-26; cuid2104; 2.12 Gigabytes in 2 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_11)
    Speaker: Ariel Rose
  - Pre-LK: The Dance and the Intellectual, 2015-09-10; cuid2105; 4.32 Gigabytes in 4 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_12)
    Speaker: Leon Wieseltier, Jed Perl, Toni Bentley, Nick Jenkins
    Location: 16 Cooper Square
    Streaming version available. Original audio/visual material is available for research onsite in the University Archives reading room. Prior notice is required for access.
  - Tripping the Line Fantastic: Al Hirschfeld & Dance, 2015-09-21; cuid2106; 4.03 Gigabytes in 8 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_13)
    Speaker: David Leopold, Author
  - Performance Tradition in Russian Opera and Ballet: A Lost Art?, 2015-10-07; cuid2107; 11.2 Gigabytes in 4 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_14)
    Speaker: Joseph Horowitz
  - Notes Towards a Ballet on a Theme of Water, 2015-10-13; cuid2108; 15.9 Gigabytes in 6 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_15)
    Speaker: Marina Warner
    Collaborators: Joanna MacGregor, Composer; Kim Brandstrup, Choreographer
  - Music and Dance: A Conversation with Mark Morris, Stephanie Jordan and Colin Fowler, 2015-10-20; cuid2109; 13.5 Gigabytes in 5 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_16)
    Speaker: Mark Morris, Stephanie Jordan, Colin Fowler, Scott Wheeler
    Speaker Type: Invited guest speaker
    Collaborators: Mark Morris, Stephanie Jordan, Colin Fowler
  - "Life is Motion": Motion in Wallace Stevens, 2015-11-04; cuid2110; 14 Gigabytes in 6 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_17)
    Event Type: Lincoln Kirstein Lecture
    Speaker: Helen Vendler
    Location: NYPL For Performing Arts, Lincoln Center
  - Mata Hari, 2015-11-16; cuid2111; 12.6 Gigabytes in 6 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_18)
    Speaker: Tarik O'Regan
  - Edward Villella on George Balanchine, 2015-11-09; cuid2112; 14.6 Gigabytes in 6 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_19)
    Event Type: Balanchine Talks
    Speaker: Edward Villella
  - Alexander/Ballet/Calder: An Alphabetical Guide to Calder and the Dance, 2015-12-03; cuid2113; 13.7 Gigabytes in 7 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_20)
    Speaker: Jed Perl
  - Ballet and British Intellectual Life: From J.M. Keynes to Antony Tudor, 2015-11-30; cuid2114; 9.37 Gigabytes in 4 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_21)
    Speaker: Laura Quinton
    Speaker Type: Graduate Assistant, CBA
    This video recording is restricted and may only be accessed with permission of the donor.
  - In Search of Lost Time: Auguste Rodin's Drawings of the Cambodian Royal Ballet, 2015-12-14; cuid2115; 8.86 Gigabytes in 5 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_22)
    Speaker: Juliet Bellow
  - Reading of Work from Fellowship, 2015-12-16; cuid2116; 5.19 Gigabytes in 3 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_23)
    Speaker: Sascha Radetsky
  - Some Drawings; Bloodflames III; Concern, Crush Desire; F.S. Intervals; 1NVERS1ONS, 2016-02-17; cuid2117; 7.69 Gigabytes in 5 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_24)
    Speaker: Nick Mauss
    Access to original audio/visual material is available for research onsite in the University Archives reading room. Prior notice is required for access.
  - A Center for Dance, 2016-03-29; cuid2118; 14.3 Gigabytes in 5 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_25)
    Speaker: Julia Foulkes
  - Open Class with Alonzo King, 2016-03-31; cuid2119; 9.5 Gigabytes in 5 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_26)
    Event Type: Open Class
    Speaker: Alonzo King
    Collaborators: Dancers from Alonzo King's company
    Location: Joan Weill Center for Dance; Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater
  - Beyond Movement: Auguste Rodin and the Dancers of His Time, 2016-04-06; cuid2120; 13.6 Gigabytes in 5 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_27)
  - Folk into Myth: Joseph Cornell at the Ballet, 2016-04-13; cuid2121; 14.3 Gigabytes in 5 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_28)
    Speaker: Marci Kwon
  - Constructing Choral Dance and Song: Cauldrons, Columns and Woven Cloths in Early Greek Art and Text, 2016-04-18; cuid2122; 14.4 Gigabytes in 5 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_29)
    Speaker: Deborah Steiner
  - Sovietizing Russian Ballet in Co-Produced Cold War Films: Two Scenes, 2016-04-27; cuid2123; 16.1 Gigabytes in 6 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_30)
    Speaker: Marsha Seifert
  - Nightingale, a Showing of Work by Melissa Barak, 2016-05-02; cuid2124; 69 Gigabytes in 5 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_31)
    Event Type: Showing
    Speaker: Melissa Barak
    Collaborators: Dancers; Scott Wheeler, Composer
  - Essays on Dance, a Reading of New Poems, 2016-05-04; cuid2125; 5.62 Gigabytes in 3 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_32)
    Speaker: Emily Hoffman
  - Tap and Ballet: Oil and Water, 2016-05-09; cuid2126; 73.1 Gigabytes in 5 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_33)
    Speaker: Brian Seibert
  - Etudes: A Showing of New Work, 2016-05-16; cuid2127; 70.2 Gigabytes in 5 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_34)
    Speaker: Preeti Vasudevan
    Collaborators: Amar Ramasar
  - *Diz-Tanz:* Distance and Dance in Nietzsche and Heidegger, 2016-09-13; cuid2129; 7.14 Gigabytes in 2 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_35)
    Speaker: Avital Ronell
  - Ballet on the Margins: Ballet in Fragile States, 2016-10-04; cuid2130; 7.63 Gigabytes in 6 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_36)
    Speaker: Dana Mills
  - Ballet Class: An American History, 2016-10-11; cuid2131; 681 Megabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_37)
    Speaker: Melissa Klapper
  - Jerome Robbins, 2016-10-18; cuid2132; 4.54 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_38)
    Speaker: Wendy Lesser
  - Inside Nijinsky's Diaries, 2016-10-24; cuid2133; 1.46 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_39)
    Speaker: Paul Giamatti, Joan Acocella, Darryl Pinckney, Larry Wolff
  - Jack Cole, Whose Jazz Choreography Electrified American Nightclubs, 2016-10-25; cuid2134; 10.1 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_40)
    Speaker: Debra Levine
  - Violence: Recode / UNDER|STAND, 2016-11-01; cuid2135; 10.1 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_41)
    Speaker: Dana Caspersen
  - Diversity and Dance: A Discussion on Race, Equity, and Other-ness in Ballet and Society, 2016-11-06; cuid2136; 760 Megabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_42)
    Speaker: Ta-Nehisi Coates, Benjamin Millepied
  - New Works for Pam Tanowitz Dance, 2016-11-08; cuid2137; 3.68 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_43)
    Speaker: Pam Tanowitz
  - Principles of Uncertainty, 2016-11-15; cuid2138; 4.44 Gigabytes in 2 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_44)
    Speaker: John Heginbotham, Maira Kalman
  - Revisiting and Reclaiming "Scheherazade," in 2016, 2016-11-22; cuid2139; 3.18 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_45)
    Speaker: Jonah Bokaer
  - The Mise-en-scene of Dreams: L'Apres-midi d'un faune, 1912, 2016-11-29; cuid2140; 12.3 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_46)
    Speaker: Emmelyn Butterfield-Rosen
  - 2016 Lincoln Kirstein Lecture: Song and Dance, 2016-12-06; cuid2142; 521 Megabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_47)
    Event Type: Public Event
    Speaker: Ian Bostridge
  - CBA Annual Celebration, 2016-12-12; cuid2143; 805 Megabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_48)
    Event Type: Special Event
    Original audio/visual material is available for research onsite in the University Archives reading room. Prior notice is required for access.
  - Breaking Bread With Balanchine: On Food, Cooking, and the Creative Impulse in Choreography and in the Kitchen, 2016-12-13; cuid2144; 5.21 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_49)
    Speaker: Meryl Rosofsky
  - In Search of Lost Time: Auguste Rodin's Drawings of the Cambodian Royal Ballet, 2016-12-14; cuid2145; 2.9 Gigabytes in 2 video files. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_50)
  - 8 Minutes, 2017-01-30; cuid2146; 4.26 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_51)
    Speaker: Alexander Whitley
  - (y)ourstory: a movement in inclusivity, 2017-03-27; cuid2147; 4.48 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_52)
    Speaker: Francesca Harper
  - Distilling Chemistry: Getting to the Heart of Partnering, 2017-04-03; cuid2148; 4.78 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_53)
    Speaker: Valeria Solomonoff
  - The Journey Taken: The Writing of Jerome Robbins, 2017-04-10; cuid2149; 4.41 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_54)
    Speaker: Amanda Vaill
  - Dance and the Emotions, 2017-04-17; cuid2150; 4.95 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_55)
    Speaker: Nancy Sherman
  - Ballet in the Cold War: A Soviet-American Exchange, 2017-05-01; cuid2153; 4.97 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_57)
    Speaker: Anne Searcy
  - Musicality, Structure, and the Classical Idiom, 2017-05-08; cuid2154; 9.31 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_58)
    Speaker: Claudia Schreier
  - The Body and Beckett, 2017-05-11; cuid2155; 2.98 Gigabytes in 1 video file. (E-records Electronic records, E-records UA_RG_37-51_ER_59)
    Speaker: Lisa Dwan